<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gene–culture Co‑evolution on SnakeCult Deep Lore</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/geneculture-coevolution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gene–culture Co‑evolution on SnakeCult Deep Lore</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/geneculture-coevolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Eve Theory of Consciousness: Solving the Wallace Problem of Human Cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/eve-theory-wallace-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/eve-theory-wallace-problem/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR&#xA;The Wallace Problem – Alfred R. Wallace judged human self‑awareness and language &amp;ldquo;over‑built&amp;rdquo; for Paleolithic life; Darwin himself had doubts. EToC – Female‑led rituals (likely snake‑venom trance) created a cultural ratchet for recursive thought, which genetics then amplified. Why it wins – Fits gradual selection, explains the 150 ky archaeological lag, predicts testable traces (venom‑resistance alleles, serpent cult sites) and outperforms self‑domestication, cooking, or &amp;ldquo;big‑mutation&amp;rdquo; stories. Introduction: The Wallace Problem in Human Evolution Why do humans alone possess language and an &amp;ldquo;inner voice&amp;rdquo; of self-reflective consciousness?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ritualised Mind and the Eve Theory of Consciousness: A Convergent Account of Human Cognitive Evolution</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/froese-ritualized-mind-eve-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/froese-ritualized-mind-eve-theory/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR&#xA;Gap - Anatomically modern brains appear ~200 kya, but symbolic culture blooms ~50 kya. Ritual trigger - Froese: altered-state initiations forge subject-object separation. Concrete mechanism - Eve Theory: female-led snake-venom rites spread the &amp;ldquo;self&amp;rdquo; meme, leaving mythic and genomic traces. Pay-off - Combined model outperforms gradualist, saltationist, and generic &amp;ldquo;stoned-ape&amp;rdquo; accounts. 1 Introduction - Why the Sapient Paradox Persists One of the enduring puzzles in human evolution is the Sapient Paradox – the disconnect between the early emergence of anatomically modern humans and the much later blossoming of fully &amp;ldquo;human&amp;rdquo; behavior .</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
