<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sapient Paradox on SnakeCult Deep Lore</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/sapient-paradox/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sapient Paradox on SnakeCult Deep Lore</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/sapient-paradox/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From Ritual to Recursion: Integrating Froese&#39;s Ritualised-Mind Hypothesis with the Eve Theory of Consciousness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/froese-etoc-hard-consciousness-synthesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/froese-etoc-hard-consciousness-synthesis/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR&#xA;Froese&amp;rsquo;s Ritualised-Mind Hypothesis (RMH) suggests ritual ordeal initiated subject-object separation. Eve Theory of Consciousness (EToC) extends RMH with specific catalysts (e.g., venom) and agents (females). This synthesis connects RMH/EToC to modern neural theories (GNW, IIT, PP, AST, HOT). 1 Problem Statement Two questions frame the evolution of human consciousness:&#xA;Installation - How did reflective subject–object separation first become part of hominin development? Implementation - What neural or informational architecture realises conscious experience in any mind, ancient or modern?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ritualised Mind and the Eve Theory of Consciousness: A Convergent Account of Human Cognitive Evolution</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/froese-ritualized-mind-eve-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/froese-ritualized-mind-eve-theory/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR&#xA;Gap - Anatomically modern brains appear ~200 kya, but symbolic culture blooms ~50 kya. Ritual trigger - Froese: altered-state initiations forge subject-object separation. Concrete mechanism - Eve Theory: female-led snake-venom rites spread the &amp;ldquo;self&amp;rdquo; meme, leaving mythic and genomic traces. Pay-off - Combined model outperforms gradualist, saltationist, and generic &amp;ldquo;stoned-ape&amp;rdquo; accounts. 1 Introduction - Why the Sapient Paradox Persists One of the enduring puzzles in human evolution is the Sapient Paradox – the disconnect between the early emergence of anatomically modern humans and the much later blossoming of fully &amp;ldquo;human&amp;rdquo; behavior .</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
